<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix version="5.0"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xml:id="bayeux">
<info>
    <title>The Bayeux Protocol Specification v 1.0</title>
    <authorgroup>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Alex</firstname>
                <surname>Russell</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Greg</firstname>
                <surname>Wilkins</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>David</firstname>
                <surname>Davis</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Mark</firstname>
                <surname>Nesbitt</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
        <year>2007</year>
        <holder>The Dojo Foundation</holder>
    </copyright>
</info>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Status of this Document</title>
</info>
<para>
    This document specifies a protocol for the Internet community, and requests
    discussion and suggestions for improvement.
    This document is written in the style and spirit of an IETF RFC but is not,
    as of yet, an official IETF RFC.
    Distribution of this document is unlimited.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Abstract</title>
</info>
<para>
    Bayeux is a protocol for transporting asynchronous messages (primarily over web protocols such as HTTP and
    WebSocket), with low latency between a web server and web clients.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Introduction</title>
</info>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Purpose</title>
</info>
<para>
    The primary purpose of Bayeux is to support responsive bidirectional interactions between
    web clients, for example using using <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX">AJAX</link>,
    and the web server.
</para>
<para>
    Bayeux is a protocol for transporting asynchronous messages (primarily over HTTP), with low latency between a web
    server and a web client.
    The messages are routed via named <emphasis>channels</emphasis> and can be delivered:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
    <para>server to client</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>client to server</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>client to client (via the server)</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
    By default, <emphasis>publish/subscribe</emphasis> routing semantics are applied to the channels.
</para>
<para>
    Delivery of asynchronous messages from the server to a web client is often described as
    <emphasis>server push</emphasis>.
    The combination of server push techniques with an AJAX web application has been called
    <emphasis>Comet</emphasis>.
    CometD is a project by the Dojo Foundation to provide multiple implementation of the Bayeux protocol
    in several programming languages.
</para>
<para>
    Bayeux seeks to reduce the complexity of developing Comet web applications
    by allowing implementers to more easily interoperate, to solve common message
    distribution and routing problems, and to provide mechanisms for incremental
    improvements and extensions.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Requirements</title>
</info>
<para>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
    "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
    interpreted as described in RFC2119. An implementation is not compliant if it
    fails to satisfy one or more of the MUST or REQUIRED level requirements for the
    protocols it implements. An implementation that satisfies all the MUST or
    REQUIRED level and all the SHOULD level requirements for its protocols is said
    to be "unconditionally compliant"; one that satisfies all the MUST level
    requirements but not all the SHOULD level requirements for its protocols is
    said to be "conditionally compliant."
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Terminology</title>
</info>
<para>
    This specification uses a number of terms to refer to the roles played by
    participants in, and objects of, Bayeux communication:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>client</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    A program that initiates the communication.
</para>
<para>
    A web client (for example, a HTTP client, but also a WebSocket client)
    is a program that initiates TCP/IP connections for the purpose of sending web requests.
    A Bayeux client initiates the Bayeux message exchange and will typically
    execute within a web client, but it is likely to have also Bayeux clients that
    execute within web servers.
</para>
<para>
    Implementations may distinguish between
    Bayeux clients running within a web client and Bayeux clients running
    within the web server. Specifically server-side Bayeux clients MAY be
    privileged clients with access to private information about other clients
    (see <xref linkend="bayeux_clientId" />) and subscriptions.
    <!--
    COMMENT:
    Consider explicitly defining the terms "remote client" and "local/server-side client".
    By saying implementations are allowed to distinguish between them, the spec is implicitly
    ack'ing the distinction anyway.  More on this later re: the handling of meta channels.
    -->
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>server</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    An application program that accepts communications from clients.
    A web server accepts TCP/IP connections in order to service web requests (HTTP requests or
    WebSocket requests) by sending back web responses.
    A Bayeux server accepts and responds to the message exchanges initiated by a Bayeux client.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>request</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    For the HTTP protocol, an HTTP request message as defined by section 5 of RFC 2616.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>response</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    For the HTTP protocol, an HTTP response message as defined by section 6 of RFC 2616.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>message</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    A message is a JSON encoded object exchanged between client and server for the
    purpose of implementing the Bayeux protocol as defined by <xref linkend="bayeux_message_fields" />,
    <xref linkend="bayeux_meta_message" /> and <xref linkend="bayeux_event_message" />,
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>event</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    Application specific data that is sent over the Bayeux protocol.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>envelope</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    The transport specific message format that wraps a standard Bayeux message.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>channel</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    A named destination and/or source of events.
    Events are published to channels and subscribers to channels receive published events.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>connection</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    A communication link that is established either permanently
    or transiently, for the purposes of messages exchange.
    A client is connected if a link is established with the server,
    over which asynchronous events can be received.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>JSON</term>
<listitem>
<para>
    JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight data-interchange format.
    It is easy for humans to read and write. It is easy for machines to parse
    and generate. It is based on a subset of the JavaScript Programming
    Language, Standard ECMA-262 3rd Edition - December 1999.
    JSON is described at <link xl:href="http://www.json.org/">http://www.json.org/</link>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Overall Operation</title>
</info>
<section xml:id="bayeux_http_transport">
<info>
    <title>HTTP Transport</title>
</info>
<para>
    The HTTP protocol is a request/response protocol. A client sends a request to
    the server in the form of a request method, URI, and protocol version, followed
    by a MIME-like message containing request modifiers, client information, and
    optional body content over a connection with a server. The server responds with
    a status line, including the message's protocol version and a success or error
    code, followed by a MIME-like message containing server information, entity
    metainformation, and possible entity-body content.
</para>
<para>
    The server may not initiate a connection with a client nor send an unrequested
    response to the client, thus asynchronous events cannot be delivered from
    server to client unless a previously issued request exists. In order to allow
    two way asynchronous communication, Bayeux supports the use of multiple HTTP
    connections between a client and server, so that previously issued requests are
    available to transport server to client messages.
</para>
<para>
    The recommendation of section 8.1.4 of RFC 2616 is that a single client
    SHOULD NOT maintain more than 2 connection with any server, thus the Bayeux
    protocol MUST NOT require any more than 2 HTTP requests to be simultaneously
    handled by a server in order to handle all application (Bayeux based or
    otherwise) requests from a client.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Non HTTP Transports</title>
</info>
<!--
    FIXME: we are currently silent on some important points:
        1.) must conforming servers which don't use HTTP *also* support one or
        more of the HTTP-based mechanisms?
        2.) must conforming servers that aren't HTTP-based support plain-text
        payloads?
-->
<para>
    While HTTP is the predominant transport protocol used on the internet, it is
    not intended that it will be the only transport for Bayeux. Other transports
    that support a request/response paradigm may be used (for example, WebSocket
    is not a request/response protocol, but supports a request/response paradigm).
    However this document assumes HTTP for reasons of clarity. When non-HTTP connection-level
    transport mechanisms are employed, conforming Bayeux servers and clients MUST
    still conform to the semantics of the JSON encoded messages outlined in this document.
</para>
<para>
    Several of the "transport types" described in this document are distinguished
    primarily by how they wrap messages for delivery over HTTP and the sequence
    and content of the HTTP connections initiated by clients. While this may seem
    like a set of implementation concerns to observant readers, the difficulties of
    creating interoperable implementations without specifying these semantics fully
    is a primary motivation for the development of this specification.
    Were the deployed universe of servers and clients more flexible, it may not
    have been necessary to develop Bayeux.
</para>
<para>
    Regardless, care has been taken in the development of this specification to
    ensure that future clients and servers which implement differing
    connection-level strategies and encodings may still evolve and continue to be
    conforming Bayeux implementations so long as they implement the JSON-based
    public/subscribe semantics outlined herein.
</para>

<note>
<para>
    The rest of this document speaks as though HTTP will be used for message transport.
</para>
</note>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>JavaScript</title>
</info>
<para>
    Bayeux clients implemented in JavaScript that run within the security
    framework of a browser MUST adhere to the restrictions imposed
    by the browser, such as the
    <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same_origin_policy">same origin policy</link>
    or the <link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/access-control/">CORS</link> specification,
    or the threading model.
    These restrictions are normally enforced by the browser itself, but nonetheless
    the client implementation must be aware of these restrictions and adhere to them.
</para>
<para>
    Bayeux clients implemented in JavaScript but not running within a browser MAY
    relax the restrictions imposed by browsers.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Client to Server event delivery</title>
</info>
<para>
    A Bayeux event is sent from the client to the server via a HTTP request
    initiated by a client and transmitted to the origin server via a chain of
    zero or more intermediaries (proxy, gateway or tunnel):
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ---------- U ---------- P ------------ O ---------- BS
 | --M0(E)--&gt; |            |              |            |
 |            | ---HTTP request(M0(E))--&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | --M0(E)--&gt; |
 |            |            |              | &lt;---M1---- |
 |            | &lt;---HTTP response(M1)---- |            |
 | &lt;---M1---  |            |              |            |
 |            |            |              |            |
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    The figure above represents a Bayeux event E encapsulated in a Bayeux message M0
    being sent from a Bayeux client BC to a Bayeux server BS via a HTTP request
    transmitted from a User Agent U to to an Origin server O via a proxy P. The
    HTTP response contains another Bayeux message M1 that will at least contain the
    protocol response to M0, but may contain other Bayeux events initiated on the
    server or on other clients.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Server to Client event delivery</title>
</info>
<para>
    A Bayeux event is sent from the server to the client via a HTTP response to
    a HTTP request sent in anticipation by a client and transmitted to an
    origin server via a chain of zero or more intermediaries (proxy, gateway or
    tunnel):
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ---------- U ---------- P ------------ O ---------- BS
 | ---M0---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | --- HTTP request(M0) ---&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M0---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 |            |            |              | &lt;--M1(E)-- |
 |            | &lt;--HTTP response(M1(E))-- |            |
 | &lt;--M1(E)-- |            |              |            |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    The figure above represents a Bayeux message M0 being sent from a Bayeux client
    BC to a Bayeux server BS via a HTTP request transmitted from a User Agent U to
    to an Origin server O via a proxy P. The message M0 is sent in anticipation of
    a Bayeux event to be delivered from server to client and the Bayeux server
    waits for such an event before sending a response. A Bayeux event E is shown
    being delivered via Bayeux message M1 in the HTTP response. M1 may contain
    zero, one or more Bayeux events destined for the Bayeux client.
</para>
<para>
    The transport used to send events from the server to the client may terminate
    the HTTP response (which does not imply that the connection is closed) after
    delivery of M1 or use techniques to leave the HTTP response uncompleted and
    stream additional messages to the client.
</para>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Polling transports</title>
</info>
<para>
    Polling transports will always terminate the HTTP response after sending all
    available Bayeux messages.
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ---------- U ---------- P ------------ O ---------- BS
 | ---M0---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | --- HTTP request(M0) ---&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M0---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 |            |            |              | &lt;--M1(E)-- |
 |            | &lt;--HTTP response(M1(E))-- |            |
 | &lt;--M1(E)-- |            |              |            |
 | ---M2---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | --- HTTP request(M2) ---&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M2---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    On receipt of the HTTP response containing M1, the Bayeux client issues a new
    Bayeux message M2 either immediately or after an interval in anticipation of
    more events to be delivered from server to client.
    Bayeux implementations MUST support a specific style of polling
    transport called <emphasis>long polling</emphasis> (see <xref linkend="bayeux_long_polling" />).
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Streaming transports</title>
</info>
<para>
    Some Bayeux transports use the <emphasis>streaming technique</emphasis> (also called the
    <emphasis>forever response</emphasis>) that allows multiple messages to be sent within the
    same HTTP response:
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ---------- U ---------- P ------------ O ---------- BS
 | ---M0---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | --- HTTP request(M0) ---&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M0---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 |            |            |              | &lt;--M1(E0)- |
 |            | &lt;--HTTP response(M1(E0))- |            |
 | &lt;--M1(E0)- |            |              |            |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 |            |            |              | &lt;--M1(E1)- |
 |            | &lt;----(M1(E1))------------ |            |
 | &lt;--M1(E1)- |            |              |            |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    Streaming techniques avoid the latency and extra messaging of anticipatory
    requests, but are subject to the implementation of user agents and proxies as they
    requires incomplete HTTP responses to be delivered to the Bayeux client.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Two connection operation</title>
</info>
<para>
    In order to achieve bidirectional communication, a Bayeux client uses 2
    HTTP connections (see <xref linkend="bayeux_http_transport" />) to a Bayeux server so that both server to client and
    client to server messaging may occur asynchronously:
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ---------- U ---------- P ------------ O ---------- BS
 | ---M0---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | ------ req0(M0) --------&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M0---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 | --M1(E1)-&gt; |            |              |            |
 |            | ----- req1(M1(E1))------&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | --M1(E1)-&gt; |
 |            |            |              | &lt;---M2---- |
 |            | &lt;---- resp1(M2)---------- |            |
 | &lt;---M2---  |            |              |            |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
 |            |            |              | &lt;-M3(E2)-- |
 |            | &lt;-----resp2(M3(E2))------ |            |
 | &lt;-M3(E2)-- |            |              |            |
 | ---M4---&gt;  |            |              |            |
 |            | ------req3(M4)----------&gt; |            |
 |            |            |              | ----M4---&gt; |
 ~            ~            ~              ~            ~ wait
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    HTTP requests req0 and req1 are sent on different TCP/IP connections, so that
    the response to req1 may be sent before the response to req0. Implementations
    MUST control HTTP pipelining so that req1 does not get queued behind req0 and
    thus enforce an ordering of responses.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Connection Negotiation</title>
</info>
<para>
    Bayeux connections are negotiated between client and server with handshake
    messages that allow the connection type, authentication and other parameters to
    be agreed upon between the client and the server.
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ----------------------------------------- BS
 | ------------------ handshake request ---&gt; |
 | &lt;---- handshake response ---------------- |
 | -------------------- connect request ---&gt; |
 ~                                           ~ wait
 | &lt;------ connect response ---------------- |
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    Bayeux connection negotiation may be iterative and several handshake messages may be
    exchanged before a successful connection is obtained. Servers may also request Bayeux
    connection renegotiation by sending an unsuccessful connect response with
    advice to reconnect with a handshake message.
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ----------------------------------------- BS
 | ------------------ handshake request ---&gt; |
 | &lt;-- unsuccessful handshake response ----- |
 | ------------------ handshake request ---&gt; |
 | &lt;-- successful handshake response ------- |
 | -------------------- connect request ---&gt; |
 ~                                           ~ wait
 | &lt;------ connect response ---------------- |
 | -------------------- connect request ---&gt; |
 | &lt;---- unsucessful connect response ------ |
 | ------------------ handshake request ---&gt; |
 | &lt;-- successful handshake response ------- |
 | -------------------- connect request ---&gt; |
 ~                                           ~ wait
 | &lt;------ connect response ---------------- |
</screen>
</informalexample>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Unconnected operation</title>
</info>
<para>
    OPTIONALLY, messages can be sent without a prior handshake (see <xref linkend="bayeux_publish" />).
</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
BC ----------------------------------------- BS
 | ------------------- message request ----&gt; |
 | &lt;---- message response ------------------ |
</screen>
</informalexample>
<para>
    This pattern is often useful when implementing non-browser clients for Bayeux
    servers. These clients often simply wish to address messages to other clients
    which the Bayeux server may be servicing, but do not wish to listen for events
    themselves.
</para>
<para>
    Bayeux servers MAY support messages sent without a prior handshake, but in any case MUST
    respond to such messages (eventually with an error message).
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title>Client State Table</title>
</info>
<informalexample>
<screen>
-------------++------------+-------------+------------+------------
State/Event  || handshake  | Timeout     | Successful | Disconnect
             ||  request   |             |   connect  |  request
             ||   sent     |             |  response  |   sent
-------------++------------+-------------+----------- +------------
UNCONNECTED  || CONNECTING | UNCONNECTED |            |
CONNECTING   ||            | UNCONNECTED | CONNECTED  | UNCONNECTED
CONNECTED    ||            | UNCONNECTED |            | UNCONNECTED
-------------++------------+-------------+------------+------------
</screen>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Protocol Elements</title>
</info>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Common Elements</title>
</info>
<para>
    The characters used for Bayeux names and identifiers are defined by the BNF definitions:
</para>
<screen>
alpha    = lowalpha | upalpha

lowalpha = "a" | "b" | "c" | "d" | "e" | "f" | "g" | "h" | "i" |
           "j" | "k" | "l" | "m" | "n" | "o" | "p" | "q" | "r" |
           "s" | "t" | "u" | "v" | "w" | "x" | "y" | "z"

upalpha  = "A" | "B" | "C" | "D" | "E" | "F" | "G" | "H" | "I" |
           "J" | "K" | "L" | "M" | "N" | "O" | "P" | "Q" | "R" |
           "S" | "T" | "U" | "V" | "W" | "X" | "Y" | "Z"

digit    = "0" | "1" | "2" | "3" | "4" | "5" | "6" | "7" | "8" | "9"

alphanum = alpha | digit

mark     = "-" | "_" | "!" | "~" | "(" | ")" | "$" | "@"

string   = *( alphanum | mark | " " | "/" | "*" | "." )

token    = ( alphanum | mark ) *( alphanum | mark )

integer  = digit *( digit )
</screen>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Channels</title>
</info>
<para>
    Channels are identified by names that are styled as the absolute path component of
    a URI without parameters as defined by RFC2396.
</para>
<screen>
channel_name     = "/"  channel_segments
channel_segments = channel_segment *( "/" channel_segment )
channel_segment  = token
</screen>
<para>
    The channel name consists of an initial "/" followed by an optional sequence of
    path segments separated by a single slash "/" character. Within a path segment,
    the character "/" is reserved.
</para>
<para>
    Channel names commencing with "/meta/" are reserved for the Bayeux protocol (see <xref linkend="bayeux_meta_channels" />).
    Channel names commencing with "/service/" have a special meaning for the Bayeux protocol
    (see <xref linkend="bayeux_service_channels" />).
    Example non-meta channel names are:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>/foo</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>/foo/bar</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>/foo-bar/(foobar)</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Channel Globbing</title>
</info>
<para>
    A set of channels may be specified with a channel globbing pattern:
</para>
<screen>
channel_pattern  = *( "/" channel_segment ) "/" wild_card
wild_card = "*" | "**"
</screen>
<para>
    The channel patterns support only trailing wildcards of either "*" to match a
    single segment or "**" to match multiple segments. Example channel patterns are:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>/foo/*</code></term>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Matches <code>/foo/bar</code> and <code>/foo/boo</code>. Does not match <code>/foo</code>,
        <code>/foobar</code> or <code>/foo/bar/boo</code>.
    </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>/foo/**</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    Matches <code>/foo/bar</code>, <code>/foo/boo</code> and <code>/foo/bar/boo</code>.
    Does not match <code>/foo</code>, <code>/foobar</code> or <code>/foobar/boo</code>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_meta_channels">
<info>
    <title>Meta Channels</title>
</info>
<para>
    The channels commencing with the "/meta/" segment are the channels used by the Bayeux
    protocol itself.
    Local server-side Bayeux clients MAY, and remote Bayeux clients SHOULD NOT, subscribe
    (see <xref linkend="bayeux_subscribe" />) to meta channels.
    Messages published to meta channels MUST NOT be distributed to remote clients
    by Bayeux servers. A server side handler of a meta channel MAY publish response
    messages that are delivered only to the client that sent the original request message.
    If a message published to a meta channel contains an id field, then any
    response messages delivered to the client MUST contain an id field with the
    same value.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_service_channels">
<info>
    <title>Service Channels</title>
</info>
<para>
    The channels commencing with the "/service/" channel segment are special channels
    designed to assist request/response style messaging.
    Messages published to service channels are not distributed to any remote Bayeux clients.
    Handlers of service channels MAY deliver response messages to the client that
    published the request message. Servers SHOULD NOT record any subscriptions they
    receive for service channels.
    If a message published to a service channel contains an id field, then any
    response messages SHOULD contain an id field with the same value or a value
    derived from the request id.
    Request/response operations are described in detail in <xref linkend="bayeux_service_channel_operation" />
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Version</title>
</info>
<para>
    A protocol version is a integer followed by an optional "." separated sequence
    of alphanumeric elements:
</para>
<screen>
version         = integer *( "." version_element )
version_element = alphanum *( alphanum | "-" | "_" )
</screen>
<para>
    Versions are compared element by element, applying normal alphanumeric
    comparison to each element.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="client_id">
<info>
    <title>Client ID</title>
</info>
<para>
    A client ID is an random, non predictable sequence of alpha numeric characters:
</para>
<screen>
clientId   =   alphanum *( alphanum )
</screen>
<para>
    Client IDs are generated by the server and SHOULD be created with a strong
    random algorithm that contains at least 128 truly random bits. Servers MUST
    ensure that client IDs are unique and SHOULD attempt to avoid reuse of client
    IDs. Client IDs are encoded for delivery as strings.
    See also <xref linkend="bayeux_clientId" />.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Messages</title>
</info>
<para>
    Bayeux messages are JSON encoded objects that contain an unordered sequence of
    name value pairs representing fields and values. Values may be a simple
    strings, numbers, boolean values, or complex JSON encoded objects or arrays.
    A Bayeux message MUST contain one and only one channel field which determines
    the type of the message and the allowable fields.
</para>
<para>
    All Bayeux messages SHOULD be encapsulated in a JSON encoded array so that multiple
    messages may be transported together. A Bayeux client or server MUST accept
    either array of messages and MAY accept a single message. The JSON encoded message or
    array of messages is itself often encapsulated in transport specific formatting
    and encodings. Below is an example Bayeux message in a JSON encoded array representing
    an event sent from a client to a server:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
    "channel": "/some/name",
    "clientId": "83js73jsh29sjd92",
    "data": { "myapp" : "specific data", value: 100 }
  }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>

</section>
<section xml:id="bayeux_message_fields">
<info>
    <title>Message Field Definitions</title>
</info>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>channel</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>channel</code> message field MUST be included in every Bayeux message to specify
    the source or destination of the message. In a request, the channel specifies
    the destination of the message, and in a response it specifies the source of
    the message.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>version</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>version</code> message field MUST be included in messages to/from the
    <code>/meta/handshake</code> channel to indicate the protocol version expected by the
    client/server.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>minimumVersion</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>minimumVersion</code> message field MAY be included in messages to/from the
    <code>/meta/handshake</code> channel to indicate the oldest protocol version that can be
    handled by the client/server.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="bayeux_supported_connections">
<info>
    <title><code>supportedConnectionTypes</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>supportedConnectionTypes</code> field is included in messages to/from the
    <code>/meta/handshake</code> channel to allow clients and servers to reveal the transports
    that are supported. The value is an array of strings, with each string
    representing a transport name. Defined connection types include:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>long-polling</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    This transport is defined in <xref linkend="bayeux_long_polling" />.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>callback-polling</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    This transport is defined in <xref linkend="bayeux_callback_polling" />
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<!-- TODO: add websocket ? -->
<varlistentry>
<term><code>iframe</code></term>
<listitem><para>
    OPTIONAL transport using the document content of a hidden iframe element.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>flash</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    OPTIONAL transport using the capabilities of a browser flash plugin.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
    All server and client implementations MUST support the <code>long-polling</code>
    connection type and SHOULD support <code>callback-polling</code>.
    All other connection types are OPTIONAL.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="bayeux_clientId">
<info>
    <title><code>clientId</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>clientId</code> message field uniquely identifies a client to the Bayeux server.
    The <code>clientId</code> message field MUST be included in every message sent to the server
    except for messages sent to the <code>/meta/handshake</code> channel and MAY be omitted in
    a publish message (see <xref linkend="bayeux_event_message" />).
    The <code>clientId</code> message field MAY be returned in message responses except for
    failed handshake requests and for publish message responses that were sent without
    <code>clientId</code>.
    However, care must be taken to not <emphasis>leak</emphasis> the <code>clientId</code>
    to other clients when broadcasting messages, because that would allow any other client to
    impersonate the client whose <code>clientId</code> was leaked.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>advice</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>advice</code> message field provides a way for servers to inform clients of their
    preferred mode of client operation so that in conjunction with server-enforced
    limits, Bayeux implementations can prevent resource exhaustion and inelegant
    failure modes.
</para>
<para>
    Furthermore, the <code>advice</code> message field provides a way for clients to inform
    servers of their preferred mode of operation so that they can better inform client-side
    applications of state changes (for example, connection state changes) that are relevant for applications.
</para>
<para>
    The <code>advice</code> field is a JSON encoded object containing general and transport specific values
    that indicate modes of operation, timeouts and other potential transport
    specific parameters. Advice fields may occur either in the top level of an advice object or
    within a transport specific section of the advice object.
</para>
<para>
    Unless otherwise specified in <xref linkend="bayeux_event_message" /> and <xref linkend="bayeux_transports" />,
    any Bayeux response message may contain an advice field.
    Advice received always supersedes any previous received advice.
</para>
<para>
    An example advice field sent by the server is:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
"advice": {
   "reconnect": "retry",
   "timeout": 30000,
   "interval": 1000,
   "callback-polling": {
       "reconnect": "handshake"
    }
}
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
    An example advice field sent by the client is:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
"advice": {
   "timeout": 0
}
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>reconnect</code> advice field</title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>reconnect</code> advice field is a string that indicates how the client should
    act in the case of a failure to connect. Defined <code>reconnect</code> advice field values are:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>retry</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    a client MAY attempt to reconnect with a <code>/meta/connect</code> message after the interval
    (as defined by <code>interval</code> advice field or client-default backoff), and with the same credentials.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>handshake</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    the server has terminated any prior connection status and the client MUST
    reconnect with a <code>/meta/handshake</code> message.
    A client MUST NOT automatically retry when a reconnect advice <code>handshake</code> has been received.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><code>none</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
    indicates a hard failure for the connect attempt.
    A client MUST respect reconnect advice <code>none</code> and MUST NOT automatically
    retry or handshake.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
    Any client that does not implement all defined values of reconnect MUST NOT
    automatically retry or handshake.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>timeout</code> advice field</title>
</info>
<para>
    An integer representing the period of time, in milliseconds, for the server to delay
    responses to the <code>/meta/connect</code> channel.
</para>
<para>
    This value is merely informative for clients.
    Bayeux servers SHOULD honor timeout advices sent by clients.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>interval</code> advice field</title>
</info>
<para>
    An integer representing the minimum period of time, in milliseconds, for a client to delay
    subsequent requests to the <code>/meta/connect</code> channel.
    A negative period indicates that the message should not be retried.
</para>
<para>
    A client MUST implement interval support, but a client MAY exceed the interval
    provided by the server. A client SHOULD implement a backoff strategy to
    increase the interval if requests to the server fail without new advice being
    received from the server.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>multiple-clients</code> advice field</title>
</info>
<para>
    This is a boolean field, which if true indicates that the server has detected
    multiple Bayeux client instances running within the same web client.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>hosts</code> advice field</title>
</info>
<para>
    This is an array of strings field, which if present indicates a list of host
    names or IP addresses that MAY be used as alternate servers with which the
    client may connect. If a client receives advice to re-handshake and the
    current server is not included in a supplied hosts list, then the client SHOULD
    try the hosts in order until a successful connection is establish. Advice
    received during handshakes with hosts in the list supersedes any previously
    received advice.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>connectionType</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>connectionType</code> message field specifies the type of transport the client
    requires for communication. The <code>connectionType</code> message field MUST be included
    in request messages to the <code>/meta/connect</code> channel. Connection types are
    listed in <xref linkend="bayeux_supported_connections"/>.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>id</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    An <code>id</code> message field MAY be included in any Bayeux message with an alpha numeric value:
</para>
<screen>
id   =   alphanum *( alphanum )
</screen>
<para>
    Generation of IDs is implementation specific and may be provided by the
    application. Messages published to <code>/meta/**</code> and <code>/service/**</code> SHOULD have
    <code>id</code> fields that are unique within the the connection.
</para>
<para>
    Messages sent in response to messages delivered to <code>/meta/**</code> channels MUST use
    the same message id as the request message.
</para>
<para>
    Messages sent in response to messages delivered to <code>/service/**</code> channels SHOULD
    use the same message id as the request message or an id derived from the
    request message id.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>timestamp</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>timestamp</code> message field SHOULD be specified in the following ISO 8601
    profile (all times SHOULD be sent in GMT time):
</para>
<screen>
YYYY-MM-DDThh:mm:ss.ss
</screen>
<para>
    A timestamp message field is OPTIONAL in all Bayeux messages.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>data</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>data</code> message field is an arbitrary JSON encoded object that contains event
    information. The <code>data</code> message field MUST be included in publish messages, and a Bayeux
    server MUST include the <code>data</code> message field in an event delivery message.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>successful</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The boolean <code>successful</code> message field is used to indicate success or failure and
    MUST be included in responses to the <code>/meta/handshake</code>, <code>/meta/connect</code>,
    <code>/meta/subscribe</code>, <code>/meta/unsubscribe</code>, <code>/meta/disconnect</code>, and publish
    channels.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>subscription</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>subscription</code> message field specifies the channels the client wishes to
    subscribe to or unsubscribe from. The <code>subscription</code> message field MUST be
    included in requests and responses to/from the <code>/meta/subscribe</code> or
    <code>/meta/unsubscribe</code> channels.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>error</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>error</code> message field is OPTIONAL in any Bayeux response.
    The <code>error</code> message field MAY indicate the type of error that occurred when a
    request returns with a false successful message. The error message field should
    be sent as a string in the following format:
</para>
<screen>
error            = error_code ":" error_args ":" error_message
                 | error_code ":" ":" error_message
error_code       = digit digit digit
error_args       = string *( "," string )
error_message    = string
</screen>
<para>
    Example error strings are:
</para>
<screen>
401::No client ID
402:xj3sjdsjdsjad:Unknown Client ID
403:xj3sjdsjdsjad,/foo/bar:Subscription denied
404:/foo/bar:Unknown Channel
</screen>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>ext</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    An <code>ext</code> message field MAY be included in any Bayeux message. Its value SHOULD be a
    JSON encoded object with top level names distinguished by implementation names (for example
    "com.acme.ext.auth").
</para>
<para>
    The contents of <code>ext</code> message field may be arbitrary values that allow extensions to be
    negotiated and implemented between server and client implementations.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>connectionId</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>connectionId</code> message field was used during development of the Bayeux protocol
    and its use is now deprecated and SHOULD not be used.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<info>
    <title><code>json-comment-filtered</code></title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>json-comment-filtered</code> message field of the handshake message is deprecated
    and SHOULD not be used.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_meta_message">
<info>
    <title>Meta Message Definitions</title>
</info>

<section xml:id="handshake"><info><title>Handshake</title></info>

<section><info><title>Handshake Request</title></info>

<para>
    A Bayeux client initiates a connection negotiation by sending a message to the
    <code>/meta/handshake</code> channel.
</para>
<para>
    In case of HTTP same domain connections, the handshake requests MUST be sent to the server
    using the <code>long-polling</code> transport, while for cross domain connections the handshake
    request MAY be sent with the <code>long-polling</code> transport and failing that with the
    <code>callback-polling</code> transport.
</para>
<para>
    A handshake request MUST contain the following message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/handshake"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>version</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        The version of the protocol supported by the client
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>supportedConnectionTypes</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        An array of the connection types supported by the client for the purposes
        of the connection being negotiated (see <xref linkend="bayeux_supported_connections" />).
        This list MAY be a subset of the connection types actually supported if
        the client wishes to negotiate a specific connection type.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    A handshake request MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>minimumVersion</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    A client SHOULD NOT send any other message in the request with a handshake
    message. A server MUST ignore any other message sent in the same request as a
    handshake message. An example handshake request is:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/handshake",
     "version": "1.0",
     "minimumVersion": "1.0beta",
     "supportedConnectionTypes": ["long-polling", "callback-polling", "iframe"]
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
<section><info><title>Handshake Response</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MUST respond to a handshake request with a handshake response
    message. How the handshake response is formatted depends on the transport that
    has been agreed between client and server.
</para>

<section><info><title>Successful Handshake Response</title></info>
<para>
    A successful handshake response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/handshake"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>version</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>supportedConnectionTypes</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        The connection types supported by the server for the purposes of the
        connection being negotiated.
        This list MAY be a subset of the connection types actually supported if the
        server wishes to negotiate a specific connection type.
        This list MUST contain at list one element in common with
        the supportedConnectionType provided in the handshake request. If there are
        no connectionTypes in common, the handshake response MUST be
        unsuccessful.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        A newly generated unique ID string.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value <code>true</code>
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    A successful handshake response MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>minimumVersion</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        same value as request message id
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>authSuccessful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value <code>true</code>, this field MAY be included to support prototype client
        implementations that required the <code>authSuccessful</code> field
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>An example successful handshake response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/handshake",
     "version": "1.0",
     "minimumVersion": "1.0beta",
     "supportedConnectionTypes": ["long-polling","callback-polling"],
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "successful": true,
     "authSuccessful": true,
     "advice": { "reconnect": "retry" }
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
<section><info><title>Unsuccessful Handshake Response</title></info>
<para>
    An unsuccessful handshake response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/handshake"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value <code>false</code>
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        a string with the description of the reason for the failure.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    An unsuccessful handshake response MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>supportedConnectionTypes</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        The connection types supported by the server for the purposes of the
        connection being negotiated. This list MAY be a subset of the connection
        types actually supported if the server wishes to negotiate a specific
        connection type.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>version</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>minimumVersion</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        same value as request message id
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>An example unsuccessful handshake response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/handshake",
     "version": "1.0",
     "minimumVersion": "1.0beta",
     "supportedConnectionTypes": ["long-polling","callback-polling"],
     "successful": false,
     "error": "Authentication failed",
     "advice": { "reconnect": "none" }
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
    For complex connection negotiations, multiple handshake messages may be
    exchanged between the Bayeux client and server. The handshake response will
    set the <code>successful</code> message field to false until the handshake process is complete.
    The <code>advice</code> and <code>ext</code> message fields may be used to communicate additional information
    needed to complete the handshake process. An unsuccessful handshake response
    with <code>reconnect</code> advice field of <code>handshake</code> is used to continue the connection
    negotiation. An unsuccessful handshake response with <code>reconnect</code> advice field of
    <code>none</code> is used to terminate connection negotiations.
</para>
<!--
	FIXME: need example of challenge-response implemented over ext field here!
-->
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section><info><title>Connect</title></info>

<section><info><title>Connect Request</title></info>

<para>
    After a Bayeux client has discovered the server's capabilities with a
    handshake exchange, a connection is established by sending a message to the
    <code>/meta/connect</code> channel. This message may be transported over any of the
    transports indicated as supported by the server in the handshake response.
</para>

<para>
    A connect request MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/connect"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>connectionType</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        The connection type used by the client for the purposes of this connection.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>

<para>
    A connect request MAY contain the message fields:
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
    A client MAY send other messages in the same HTTP request with a connection
    message. A server MUST handle any other message sent in the same request as a
    connect message after the handling of the connect message is complete.
</para>

<para>An example connect request is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/connect",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "connectionType": "long-polling"
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
    A transport MUST maintain one and only one outstanding connect message. When a
    HTTP response that contains a <code>/meta/connect</code> response terminates, the client
    MUST wait at least the <code>interval</code> specified in the last received <code>advice</code> before
    following the advice to reestablish the connection.
</para>
</section>

<section><info><title>Connect Response</title></info>

<para>
    A Bayeux server MUST respond to a connect request with a connect response
    message over the same transport used for the request.
</para>

<para>
    A Bayeux server MAY wait to respond until there are event messages available in
    the subscribed channels for the client that need to be delivered to the client.
</para>

<para>
    A connect responses MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>value MUST be "/meta/connect"</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>boolean indicating the success or failure of the connection</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>A connect response MAY contain the message fields:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>same value as request message id</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>timestamp</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>An example connect response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/connect",
     "successful": true,
     "error": "",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "timestamp": "12:00:00 1970",
     "advice": { "reconnect": "retry" }
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
    The client MUST maintain only a single outstanding connect message. If the
    server does not have a current outstanding connect and a connect is not
    received within a configured timeout, then the server SHOULD act as if a
    disconnect message has been received.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section><info><title>Disconnect</title></info>

<section><info><title>Disconnect Request</title></info>

<para>
    When a connected client wishes to cease operation it should send a request to
    the <code>/meta/disconnect</code> channel for the server to remove any client-related state. The
    server SHOULD release any waiting meta message handlers. Bayeux client
    applications SHOULD send a disconnect request when the user shuts down a
    browser window or leaves the current page. A Bayeux server SHOULD NOT rely
    solely on the client sending a disconnect message to remove client-related state
    information because a disconnect message might not be sent from the client or
    the disconnect request might not reach the server.
</para>
<para>
    A disconnect request MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/disconnect"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>

<para>
    A disconnect request MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example disconnect request is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/disconnect",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r"
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>

<section><info><title>Disconnect Response</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MUST respond to a disconnect request with a disconnect
    response.
</para>
<para>
    A disconnect response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/disconnect"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        boolean value indicated the success or failure of the disconnect request
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>

<para>
    A disconnect response MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>same value as request message id</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example disconnect response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/disconnect",
     "successful": true
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_subscribe"><info><title>Subscribe</title></info>

<section><info><title>Subscribe Request</title></info>

<para>
    A connected Bayeux client may send subscribe messages to register interest in a
    channel and to request that messages published to that channel are
    delivered to itself.
</para>

<para>
    A subscribe request MUST contain the message fields:
</para>

<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem>
    <para>
        value MUST be "/meta/subscribe"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>subscription</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        a channel name or a channel pattern or an array of channel names and
        channel patterns.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    A subscribe request MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>An example subscribe request is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/subscribe",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "subscription": "/foo/**"
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
<section><info><title>Subscribe Response</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MUST respond to a subscribe request with a subscribe response message.
</para>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MAY send event messages for the client in the same HTTP
    response as the subscribe response, including events for the channels just
    subscribed to.
</para>
<para>
    A subscribe response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>value MUST be "/meta/subscribe"</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>boolean indicating the success or failure of the subscribe</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>subscription</code></term>
    <listitem><para>a channel name or a channel pattern or an array of channel names and channel patterns.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>A subscribe response MAY contain the message fields:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>same value as request message id</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>timestamp</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example successful subscribe response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/subscribe",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "subscription": "/foo/**",
     "successful": true,
     "error": ""
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>An example failed subscribe response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/subscribe",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "subscription": "/bar/baz",
     "successful": false,
     "error": "403:/bar/baz:Permission Denied"
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>

<section><info><title>Unsubscribe</title></info>
<section><info><title>Unsubscribe Request</title></info>
<para>
    A connected Bayeux client may send unsubscribe messages to cancel interest in a
    channel and to request that messages published to that channel are not
    delivered to itself.
</para>
<para>
    An unsubscribe request MUST contain the message fields:
</para>

<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        value MUST be "/meta/unsubscribe"
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>subscription</code></term>
    <listitem><para>
        a channel name or a channel pattern or an array of channel names and
        channel patterns.
    </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>
    An unsubscribe request MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>An example unsubscribe request is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/unsubscribe",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "subscription": "/foo/**"
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
<section><info><title>Unsubscribe Response</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MUST respond to a unsubscribe request with a unsubscribe response message.
</para>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MAY send event messages for the client in the same HTTP response as the unsubscribe response,
    including events for the channels just unsubscribed to as
    long as the event was processed before the unsubscribe request.
</para>

<para>
    An unsubscribe response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>value MUST be "/meta/unsubscribe"</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>boolean indicating the success or failure of the unsubscribe operation</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>subscription</code></term>
    <listitem><para>a channel name or a channel pattern or an array of channel names and channel patterns.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
<para>A unsubscribe response MAY contain the message fields:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>same value as request message id</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>timestamp</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example unsubscribe response is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/meta/unsubscribe",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "subscription": "/foo/**",
     "successful": true,
     "error": ""
   }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_event_message">
<info>
    <title>Event Message Definitions</title>
</info>
<para>
    Application events are published in event messages sent from a Bayeux client to
    a Bayeux server and are delivered in event messages sent from a Bayeux server to a Bayeux client.
</para>
<section xml:id="bayeux_publish"><info><title>Publish</title></info>
<section><info><title>Publish Request</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux client can publish events on a channel by sending event messages.
    An event message MAY be sent in new HTTP request or it MAY be sent in the same HTTP request as
    any message other than a handshake meta message.
</para>

<para>
    A publish message MAY be sent from an unconnected client (that has not performed handshaking and thus does
    not have a client ID). It is OPTIONAL for a server to accept unconnected publish requests and they
    should apply server specific authentication and authorization before doing so.
</para>

<para>
    A publish event message MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The channel to which the message is published</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>data</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The message data as an arbitrary JSON encoded object</para></listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>

<para>
    A publish event message MAY contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>clientId</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The client ID returned in the handshake response</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>A unique ID for the message generated by the client</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example event message is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/some/channel",
     "clientId": "Un1q31d3nt1f13r",
     "data": "some application string or JSON encoded object",
     "id": "some unique message id"
  }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
<section><info><title>Publish Response</title></info>
<para>
    A Bayeux server MAY respond to a publish event message with a publish event acknowledgement.
</para>
<para>
    A publish event message response MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The channel to which the message was published</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>successful</code></term>
    <listitem><para>boolean indicating the success or failure of the publish</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>A publish event response MAY contain the message fields:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>error</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example event reponse message is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/some/channel",
     "successful": true,
     "id": "some unique message id"
  }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>

<section><info><title>Delivery of event messages</title></info>

<para>
    Event messages MUST be delivered to clients if the client is subscribed to the channel of the event message.
    Event messages MAY be sent to the client in the same HTTP response as any other message other than a
    <code>/meta/handshake</code> response.
    If a Bayeux server has multiple HTTP requests from the same client, the server SHOULD deliver all available messages
    in the HTTP response that will be sent immediately in preference to waking a waiting connect meta message request.
    Event message delivery MAY not acknowledged by the client.
</para>

<para>
    A deliver event message MUST contain the message fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>channel</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The channel to which the message was published</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>data</code></term>
    <listitem><para>The message as an arbitrary JSON encoded object</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>A deliver event response MAY contain the message fields:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>id</code></term>
    <listitem><para>Unique message ID from the publisher</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>ext</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>advice</code></term>
    <listitem><para> </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>An example event deliver message is:</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="json">
[
  {
     "channel": "/some/channel",
     "data": "some application string or JSON encoded object",
     "id": "some unique message id"
  }
]
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_transports">
<info>
    <title>Transports</title>
</info>

<section xml:id="bayeux_long_polling">
<info>
    <title>The <code>long-polling</code> Transport</title>
</info>
<para>
    The "long-polling" transport is a polling transport that attempts to minimize both latency in server-client
    message delivery, and the processing/network resources required for the connection.
    In "traditional" polling, servers send and terminate responses to
    requests immediately, even when there are no events to deliver, and worst-case latency is the polling delay
    between each client request.
    Long-polling server implementations attempt to hold open each request until there are events to deliver;
    the goal is to always have a pending request available to use for delivering events as they occur, thereby
    minimizing the latency in message delivery.
    Increased server load and resource starvation are addressed by using the reconnect and
    interval advice fields to throttle clients, which in the worst-case degenerate to traditional polling behaviour.
</para>

<section><info><title>The <code>long-polling</code> request messages</title></info>
<para>
    Messages SHOULD be sent to the server as the body of an <code>application/json</code>
    HTTP POST request with UTF-8 encoding.
    Alternatively, messages MAY be sent to the server as the <varname>message</varname> parameter of a
    <code>application/x-www-form-urlencoded</code> encoded POST request.
    If sent as form encoded, the Bayeux messages are sent as the <varname>message</varname> parameter in one of
    the following forms as:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Single valued and contain a single Bayeux message</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Single valued and contain an array of Bayeux message</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Multi valued and contain a several individual Bayeux message</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Multi valued and contain a several arrays of Bayeux message</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Multi valued and contain a mix of individual Bayeux messages and arrays of Bayeux message</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section><info><title>The <code>long-polling</code> response messages</title></info>
<para>
    Messages SHOULD be sent to the client as unencapsulated body content of a
    HTTP POST response with content type <code>application/json</code> with UTF-8 encoding.
</para>
<para>
    A <code>long-polling</code> response message may contain an advice field containing transport-specific
    fields to indicate the mode of operation of the transport.
    For the <code>long-polling</code> transport, the advice field MAY contain the following fields:
</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
    <term><code>timeout</code></term>
    <listitem><para>the number of milliseconds the server will hold the long poll request</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>interval</code></term>
    <listitem>
        <para>the number of milliseconds the client SHOULD wait before issuing another long poll request</para>
    </listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_callback_polling"><info><title>The <code>callback-polling</code> Transport</title></info>
<section><info><title>The <code>callback-polling</code> request messages</title></info>
<para>
    Messages SHOULD be sent to the server as the <varname>message</varname> parameter of a url encoded
    HTTP GET request.
</para>
</section>
<section><info><title>The <code>callback-polling</code> response messages</title></info>
<para>
    Responses are sent wrapped in a JavaScript callback in order to facilitate delivery.
    As specified by the <link xl:href="en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSONP">JSONP</link> pseudo-protocol,
    the name of the callback to be triggered
    is passed to the server via the <varname>jsonp</varname> HTTP GET parameter.
    In the absence of such a parameter, the name of the callback defaults to <varname>jsonpcallback</varname>.
    The called function will be passed a JSON encoded array of Bayeux messages.
</para>
<para>
    A <code>callback-polling</code> response message may contain an advice field containing transport-specific
    fields to indicate the mode of operation of the transport.
    For the <code>callback-polling</code> transport, the advice field MAY contain the following fields:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>timeout</code></term>
    <listitem><para>the number of milliseconds the server will hold the long poll request</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
    <term><code>interval</code></term>
    <listitem>
        <para>the number of milliseconds the client SHOULD wait before issuing another long poll request</para>
    </listitem>
</varlistentry></variablelist>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Security</title>
</info>

<section><info><title>Authentication</title></info>
<para>The Bayeux protocol may be used with:</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>No authentication</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        Container supplied authentication (e.g. BASIC authentication or cookie managed session
        based authentication)
    </para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>
        Bayeux extension authentication that exchanges authentication credentials
        and tokens within Bayeux messages <code>ext</code> fields
    </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
    For Bayeux authentication, no algorithm is specified for generating or
    validating security credentials or token. This version of the protocol only
    defines that the <code>ext</code> field may be used to exchange authentication challenges,
    credentials, and tokens and that the <code>advice</code> field may be used to control
    multiple iterations of the exchange.
</para>
<para>
    The connection negotiation mechanism may be used to negotiate authentication or
    request re-authentication.
</para>
</section>

<section><info><title>AJAX Hijacking</title></info>
<para>
    The AJAX hijacking vulnerability is when an attacking web site uses a script
    tag to execute JSON encoded content obtained from an AJAX server. The Bayeux protocol
    is not vulnerable to this style of attack when cookies are not used for
    authentication and a valid client ID is needed before private client data is
    returned. The use of POST by some transports further protects against this style of
    attack.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_multiple_clients">
<info>
    <title>Multiple clients operation</title>
</info>

<para>
    Current HTTP client implementations are RECOMMENDED to allow only 2
    connections between a client and a server. This presents a problem when
    multiple instances of the Bayeux client are operating in multiple tabs or
    windows of the same browser instance. The 2 connection limit can be consumed
    by outstanding connect meta messages from each tab or window and thus prevent
    other messages from being delivered in a timely fashion.
</para>

<section><info><title>Server-side Multiple clients detection</title></info>

<para>
    It is RECOMMENDED that Bayeux server implementations use the cookie
    "BAYEUX_BROWSER" to identify a HTTP client and to thus detect multiple Bayeux
    clients running within the same HTTP client. Once detected, the server SHOULD
    not wait for messages in connect and SHOULD use the advice interval mechanism
    to establish traditional polling.
</para>
</section>

<section><info><title>Client-side Multiple clients handling</title></info>
<para>
    It is RECOMMENDED that Bayeux client implementations use client side
    persistence or cookies to detect multiple intances of Bayeux clients running
    within the same HTTP client. Once detected, the user MAY be offered the option
    to disconnect all but one of the clients. It MAY be possible for client
    implementations to use client side persistence to share a Bayeux client
    instance.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="bayeux_service_channel_operation">
<info>
    <title>Request / Response operation with service channels</title>
</info>
<para>
    The publish/subscribe paradigm that is directly supported by the Bayeux
    protocol is difficult to use to efficiently implement the request/response
    paradigm between a client and a server. The <code>/service/**</code> channel space has been
    designated as a special channel space to allow efficient transport of
    application request and responses over Bayeux channels. Messages published to
    service channels are not distributed to other Bayeux clients so these channels
    can be used for private requests between a Bayeux client and a Bayeux server.
</para>
<para>
    A trivial example would be an echo service, that sent any message received from
    a client back to that client unaltered. Bayeux clients would subscribe the the
    <code>/service/echo</code> channel, but the Bayeux server would not need to record this
    subscription. When a client publishes a message to the <code>/service/echo</code> channel,
    it will be delivered only to server-side subscribers (in an implementation
    dependent fashion). The server side subscriber for the echo service would handle
    each message received by publishing a response directly to the client
    regardless of any subscription. As the client has subscribed to <code>/service/echo</code>,
    the response message will be routed correctly within the client to the
    appropriate subscription handler.
</para>
</section>
</appendix>
