<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                             http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:id="contribute">
<info>
    <title>Contributing to CometD</title>
</info>
<para>
    You can contribute to the CometD projects in several ways.
    The CometD project values your contribution, of <emphasis>any</emphasis> kind, and participating
    in mailing lists, submitting bugs or documentation enhancements is equally important as contributing code.
</para>

<simplesect id="contribute_mailing_lists">
<info>
    <title>Contributing via Mailing Lists</title>
</info>
<para>
    The simplest way to contribute to the CometD project is to subscribe to the CometD mailing lists.
    There are two mailing lists:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">cometd-users@googlegroups.com</emphasis>, to
                be used for discussions about how to use CometD. This is a low traffic mailing list.
                To subscribe to this list, go to the
                <link xl:href="http://groups.google.com/group/cometd-users/">mailing list home page</link>
                and follow the instructions to apply for membership.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">cometd-dev@googlegroups.com</emphasis>, to
                be used for discussions about the CometD implementation. This is a low traffic mailing list.
                To subscribe to this list, go to the
                <link xl:href="http://groups.google.com/group/cometd-dev/">mailing list home page</link>
                and follow the instructions to apply for membership.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    New members can join immediately the mailing list and receive messages, but their first post will be
    subject to moderation. If you post for the first time, please allow some hour to moderators to review
    the message and approve your post. This is done to reduce spam to the minimum possible.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect id="contribute_issue_reporting">
<info>
    <title>Contributing by Reporting Issues</title>
</info>
<para>
    The CometD project maintains a <link xl:href="http://bugs.cometd.org">JIRA issue tracker</link> that
    is used to submit issues about the CometD project, from bugs to feature requests, to documentation tasks,
    etc. Virtually every activity is tracked in this JIRA instance.
</para>
<para>
    In order to submit an issue, you must have a valid Dojo Foundation login.
</para>
<para>
    If you do not have one already, you can create one by visiting
    <link xl:href="http://my.dojofoundation.org/register">this link</link>.
    Choose your username and password, follow the instructions, and once your account is created,
    do not try to login to the Dojo foundation, as you do not need to.
    Go back to JIRA and login to JIRA with the account you just created.
</para>
<para>
    Once you are logged in into JIRA, you will be able to submit new issues and browse and comment existing ones.
    JIRA is a very nice issue tracking tool, and you can customize to your needs.
    For more information about JIRA, see the
    <link xl:href="http://www.atlassian.com/software/jira">JIRA documentation</link>.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect id="contribute_code">
<info>
    <title>Contributing Code Fixes and Enhancements</title>
</info>
<para>
    The CometD project code is hosted at <link xl:href="https://github.com/cometd">GitHub CometD Organization</link>.
    The repository for the CometD libraries is
    <link xl:href="https://github.com/cometd/cometd">https://github.com/cometd/cometd</link>.
    You can build the CometD project yourself by following the instruction in <xref linkend="build" />.
</para>
<para>
    In order to contribute code, you need to have a Contributor License Agreement (CLA) with the Dojo Foundation.
</para>
<para>
    Don't worry ! It's easy and you can fill it online.
    Since contributing code normally requires also interaction with JIRA, it is best if you already have a
    Dojo Foundation account before filling the CLA. See <xref linkend="contribute_issue_reporting" /> for how
    to create a Dojo Foundation account.
</para>
<para>
    Go to the <link xl:href="http://dojofoundation.org/about/claForm">Dojo Foundation CLA online form</link>,
    read it carefully and fill in the form at the bottom of the page.
    Once you have the CLA in place, you can contribute code via
    <link xl:href="https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests">GitHub pull requests</link>.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect id="contribute_documentation">
<info>
    <title>Contributing to Documentation &amp; Tutorials</title>
</info>
<para>
    The repository for the CometD documentation is
    <link xl:href="https://github.com/cometd/cometd-documentation">https://github.com/cometd/cometd-documentation</link>,
    while the repository for the CometD tutorials is
    <link xl:href="https://github.com/cometd/cometd-tutorials">https://github.com/cometd/cometd-tutorials</link>.
    The CometD documentation and tutorials are written in <link xl:href="http://www.docbook.org/">DocBook</link>,
    and built using Maven.
</para>
<para>
    There is no need for a Contributor License Agreement to contribute fixes or enhancements to the documentation
    or the tutorials, you can just contribute via
    <link xl:href="https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests">GitHub pull requests</link>.
</para>
</simplesect>
</chapter>
