<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="installation">
<info>
    <title>CometD Installation</title>
</info>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Downloading and Installing</title>
</info>
<para>
    You can download the CometD distribution from
    <link xl:href="http://download.cometd.org/">http://download.cometd.org</link>.
</para>
<para>
    Then unpack the distribution in a directory of your choice:
<screen><![CDATA[
$ tar zxvf cometd-<version>.tgz
$ cd cometd-<version>/
]]>
</screen>
</para>
<para>
    The CometD Demos contain:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        <para>
            Two full chat applications (one developed with Dojo, one with jQuery).
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>
            Examples of extensions such as message acknowledgement, reload, timesync and
            timestamp.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>
            An example of how to echo private messages to a particular client only.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>
            Clustered Auction demo (using the Oort clustering).
        </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
<title>Running the Demos</title>
</info>
<para>
To try out the CometD demos shipped with the distribution, you need a <productname>Java</productname>
Development Kit (JDK) - version 5.0 or later, and either
<link xl:href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</link>, version 3 or later, or
a compliant servlet 2.5 container such as <link xl:href="http://eclipse.org/jetty">Jetty</link>.
</para>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Running the Demos with Maven</title>
</info>
<para>
    Maven requires you to set up the <code>JAVA_HOME</code> environment variable to point to your
    JDK installation.
</para>
<para>
    After that, running the CometD demos is very simple.
    Assuming that <filename>$COMETD</filename> is the CometD installation directory, and that you have the
    <application>mvn</application> executable in your path:
    <screen>
$ cd $COMETD
$ cd cometd-demo
$ mvn jetty:deploy-war
    </screen>
</para>
<para>
    The last command starts an embedded Jetty that listens on port 8080.
    Now point your browser to <link xl:href="http://localhost:8080">http://localhost:8080</link>,
    to see the CometD Demos main page.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<info>
    <title>Running the Demos with Jetty or Another Servlet Container</title>
</info>
<para>
    In the <filename>$COMETD/cometd-demo/target</filename> directory you can find a deployable WAR
    file that can be deployed in any servlet container.
    Refer to the servlet container configuration manual to learn how to deploy the WAR in your servlet
    container.
</para>
</section>
</section>

</chapter>
