<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="java_server_multiple_sessions">
<info>
    <title>CometD 2 and Multiple Sessions</title>
</info>
<para>
The <link xl:href="http://ietf.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt">HTTP protocol</link> recommends a connection limit of two connections per domain.
While modern browsers are configured by default with more than two connections per domain, it is not safe to make such an assumption; thus any iframes, tabs or windows on the same browser connecting to the same host need to share two connections.
</para>
<para>
If two iframes/tabs/windows initiate a Bayeux communication, both starts a long poll connect request and both connections are consumed, making it impossible to send another Bayeux request (for example, a publish) until one of the two long polls returns.
</para>
<para>
The CometD Server implements the <link xl:href="http://svn.cometd.com/trunk/bayeux/bayeux.html#toc_35">multiple-clients advice</link> as set forth in the Bayeux specification.
The server uses <code>BAYEUX_BROWSER</code> cookie to detect multiple CometD clients from the same browser.
</para>
<para>
If the CometD server detects multiple clients, only one long poll connection is allowed and subsequent long poll requests do not wait for messages before returning. They return immediately with the <code>multiple-clients</code> field of the advice object set to true. The advice also contains an <code>interval</code> field set to the value of the <code>multiSessionInterval</code> servlet init parameter (see <xref linkend="java_server_configuration" />). This instructs the client not to send another poll until that interval has passed.
The effect of this advice is that additional client connections normally poll the server with a period of <code>multiSessionInterval</code>. This avoids consuming both HTTP connections at the cost of some latency for the additional iframes/tabs/windows.
</para>
<para>
We recommend that the client application monitor the <code>/meta/connect</code> channel for <code>multiple-clients</code> field in the advice. If detected, the application might ask the user to close the additional tabs, or it could automatically close them, or take some other action.
</para>
<para>
Non-browser clients (or browsers with cookies disabled) must handle the <code>BAYEUX_BROWSER</code> cookie with the same semantic of browsers, or configure the server to allow multiple sessions even without <code>BAYEUX_BROWSER</code> information via the <code>allowMultiSessionsNoBrowser</code> servlet init parameter (see <xref linkend="java_server_configuration" />).
</para>
</section>
