<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="java_server_authorization">
<info>
    <title>CometD Java Server API: Authorization</title>
</info>
<para>
You can configure the Bayeux object with a <code>org.cometd.bayeux.server.SecurityPolicy</code> object, which allows you to control various steps of the Bayeux protocol such as handshake, subscription, and publish. By default, the Bayeux object does not have a SecurityPolicy, which means that any operation is authorized.
</para>
<para>
The <code>org.cometd.bayeux.server.SecurityPolicy</code> has a default implementation in <code>org.cometd.server.DefaultSecurityPolicy</code>, that is useful as a base class to customize the SecurityPolicy (see how <link xl:href="/documentation/2.x/howtos/authentication">authentication</link> works for an example).
</para>
<para>
The <code>org.cometd.bayeux.server.SecurityPolicy</code> methods are:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
boolean canHandshake(BayeuxServer server, ServerSession session, ServerMessage message);

boolean canCreate(BayeuxServer server, ServerSession session, String channelId, ServerMessage message);

boolean canSubscribe(BayeuxServer server, ServerSession session, ServerChannel channel, ServerMessage messsage);

boolean canPublish(BayeuxServer server, ServerSession session, ServerChannel channel, ServerMessage messsage);
]]>
</programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
The methods control, respectively, whether a handshake, a channel creation, a subscription to a channel or a publish to a channel are to be authorized.
</para>
<para>
The default implementation <code>org.cometd.server.DefaultSecurityPolicy</code>:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Allows any handshake.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Allows creation of a channel only from clients that performed a handshake, and only if the channel is not a meta channel.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Allows subscription from clients that performed a handshake, but not if the channel is a meta channel.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Allows publish from clients that performed a handshake to any channel that is not a meta channel.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
To understand how to install your custom <code>SecurityPolicy</code> on the Bayeux object, see how it is done in the <link xl:href="/documentation/2.x/howtos/authentication">authentication</link> howto.
</para>
<para>
Follow also the section on <link xl:href="/documentation/2.x/cometd-java/server/authorizers">authorizers</link>.
</para>
</section>