<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
         xml:id="javascript_publish">
<info>
    <title>Publishing</title>
</info>
<para>
    The <code>publish()</code> method allows you to publish data onto a certain channel:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
cometd.publish('/mychannel', { mydata: { foo: 'bar' } });
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
    You cannot (and it makes no sense to) publish to a meta channel, but you can publish to a service
    or broadcast channel even if you are not subscribed to that channel.
    However, you have to handshake (see <xref linkend="javascript_handshake" />) before you can publish.
</para>
<para>
    As with other JavaScript CometD API, <code>publish()</code> involves a communication with the server and it is
    asynchronous: it returns immediately, well before the Bayeux server has received the message.
</para>
<para>
    When the message you published arrives to the server, the server replies to the client with a publish
    acknowledgment; this allows clients to be sure that the message reached the server.
    The publish acknowledgment arrives on the same channel the message was published to, with the same
    message <code>id</code>, with a <code>successful</code> field.
    If the message publish fails for any reason, for example because server cannot be reached, then a publish
    failure will be emitted, similarly to publish acknowledgments.
</para>
<para>
    For historical reasons, publish acknowledgments and failures are notified on the <code>/meta/publish</code>
    channel (only in the JavaScript library), even if the <code>/meta/publish</code> channel is not part of
    <xref linkend="bayeux" />.
</para>
<para>
    In order to be notified of publish acknowledgments or failures, is it recommended that you use this variant
    of the <code>publish()</code> function, passing a callback function:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
cometd.publish('/mychannel', { mydata: { foo: 'bar' } }, function(publishReply)
{
    if (publishReply.successful)
    {
        // The message reached the server
    }
});
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<note>
<para>
    Calling <code>publish()</code> <emphasis role="bold"> does not </emphasis> mean that you have published
    the message when <code>publish()</code> returns.
</para>
</note>
<para>
    If you need to publish several messages to different channels, you might want to use
    <xref linkend="javascript_batch" />.
</para>
</section>
