<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
         xml:id="javascript_handshake">
<info>
    <title>Handshaking</title>
</info>
<para>
The call to <code>handshake()</code> (or to <code>init()</code>) initiates the Bayeux communication with the Bayeux server.
</para>
<para>
The Bayeux handshake performs two tasks:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
    <para>The client and the server negotiate the type of transport to use.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>Once the transport negotiates successfully, the server informs the client with the detailed timings of the
        requests.
    </para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
    As with several methods of the JavaScript CometD API, it is an asynchronous method: it returns immediately, well
    before the Bayeux handshake steps have completed.
</para>
<note>
<para>
    Calling <code>handshake()</code> <emphasis role="bold"> does not</emphasis> mean that you have completed the
    handshake with the server when <code>handshake()</code> returns.
</para>
</note>
<para>
The handshake might fail for several reasons:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>You mistyped the server URL.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The transport could not be negotiated successfully.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The server denied the handshake (for example, the authentication credentials were wrong).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The server crashed.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>There was a network failure.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
    Therefore it is not a good idea to write this code:
</para>
<informalexample>
<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
// Configure and handshake
cometd.init('http://localhost:8080/cometd');

// Publish to a channel
cometd.publish('/foo', { foo: 'bar' });
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
    It is not a good idea because there is no guarantee that the call to <code>publish()</code> (see
    <xref linkend="javascript_publish" />) can actually succeed in contacting the Bayeux server.
    Since the API is asynchronous, you have no way of knowing synchronously (that is, by having <code>handshake()</code>
    return an error code or by throwing an exception) that the handshake failed.
    Even if the handshake succeeds, you might still be disconnected from the Bayeux server, for example because the
    server crashed just after the successful handshake.
    Fortunately there is a way to receive notifications about the details of the Bayeux protocol message exchange: by
    adding listeners to special channels (called <emphasis>meta channels</emphasis>).
    <xref linkend="javascript_subscribe" /> section explains this functionality.
</para>
</section>
