<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="preface">
<title>Preface</title>
<para>
    <link xl:href="http://cometd.org/">CometD</link>
    is a scalable web event routing bus that allows you to write low-latency, server-side, event-driven web applications.
    Typical examples of such applications are stock trading applications, web chat applications, online games, and
    monitoring consoles.
</para>
<para>
    CometD makes use of an
    <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX">Ajax</link>
    push technology pattern known as
    <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comet_(programming)">Comet</link>, but also
    uses emerging web standards such as
    <link xl:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebSocket">WebSocket</link>
    for low latency communication.
</para>
<para>
    The CometD project provides <productname>Java</productname> and <productname>JavaScript</productname>
    libraries that allow you to write
    low-latency, server-side, event-driven web applications in a simple and portable way. You can therefore
    concentrate on the business side of your application rather than worrying about low-level details such
    as the transport (HTTP or WebSocket), the scalability and the robustness.
    The CometD libraries provide these latter characteristics.
</para>
<para>
    If you are new to CometD, you can follow this learning path:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
    Read <xref linkend="installation" /> to download, install CometD and to try out its demos.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Read <xref linkend="primer" /> to get your hands dirty with CometD with a step-by-step tutorial.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Read <xref linkend="concepts" /> to understand the abstractions that CometD defines.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    <!-- TODO: link to the tutorials ? -->
    Study the CometD demos that ship with the CometD distribution <!--(see <xref linkend="intallation_demos" />)-->.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Read the rest of this reference book for further details.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>You can contribute to the CometD project and be involved in the CometD community, including:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
    Trying it out and reporting issues at
    <link xl:href="http://bugs.cometd.org">http://bugs.cometd.org</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Participating in the <link xl:href="http://groups.google.com/group/cometd-users/">CometD Users</link>
    and <link xl:href="http://groups.google.com/group/cometd-dev/">CometD Development</link> mailing lists.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Helping out with the documentation by contacting the mailing lists or by reporting issues.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Spreading the word about CometD in your organization.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</preface>
