<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd
                             http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:id="support">
<info>
    <title>CometD Commercial Support Services</title>
</info>
<para>
    The services provided are provided directly by the CometD committers, ensuring the maximum result.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
    CometD training of your developers. Training includes tips and tricks, experience gained by developing
    CometD applications over the year and much more.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Development of proof-of-concept applications. We can develop these much quicker than developers not
    well experienced in CometD.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Development of an application framework tailed for your needs. Your developers can concentrate more
    on the implementation of the application rather than CometD details.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Development of custom CometD features. Nothing like real-world use cases to improve an open source
    project like CometD.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    CometD advices to your developers. Your development team has direct access to CometD experts to ask
    questions or opinions, so that mistakes are caught early when they cost less rather than later when
    they will cost a lot more.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    CometD application review. If you have already developed your CometD application, we can review it
    and suggest fixes or improvements to make it better.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    CometD performance tuning. If your CometD application scales only up to a certain point, we can review
    its performance and suggest the best changes to apply to make it scale better.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    CometD clustering review. If you need to scale horizontally, CometD provides a scalability cluster,
    see <xref linkend="java_oort" />. Clustering is never easy, but we can suggest the right approach
    to make your application clusterable.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
    Any other CometD-related service that you may need, we can provide it.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
    <link xl:href="https://webtide.com">Webtide</link>, the company that was formerly providing CometD
    commercial support, is now part of <link xl:href="http://intalio.com">Intalio</link>.
</para>
<para>
    Intalio provides <link xl:href="http://www.intalio.com/products/jetty/cometd/">commercial support</link>
    for the CometD project.
</para>
<para>
    <link xl:href="https://www.webtide.com/contact/">Contact us</link> for any information you need,
    no obligations on your part.
</para>

</chapter>
